Guide to the Michael Malone Papers, 1970s-2017 RL.00839
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Michael Malone papers
1970s-2017
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Malone, Michael, 1942-
RL.00839
1313
33.5 Linear Feet
Best-selling author and daytime television writer from Durham, N.C. The collection chiefly contains drafts and galleys of Malone's novels and other writings, personal and professional correspondence, and teaching materials. Also included are contracts and royalty statements, book tour materials and other promotional materials, videocassettes, audiocassettes, newspaper reviews and clippings, and digital files. The bulk of materials relate to Malone's career as a novelist and as a writer for the popular soap operas One Life to Live and Another World.
33.5 linear feet
Access Restrictions
Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Contact Research Services to request the production of use copies.
Provenance
The Michael Malone Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in August 2008, July 2009, April 2012, and July 2017.
Biographical Note
Michael Malone is a novelist and television writer from Durham, North Carolina. Educated at the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill and Harvard University, Malone taught at the University of Pennsylvania and Yale but is best known for his work as an author and a writer for the soap operas One Life to Live and Another World. Malone won a 1994 Daytime Emmy Award for Best Writing for his work on One Life to Live. Malone is married to Maureen Quilligan, a professor of English at Duke University. The couple reside at Burnside, a historic home in Hillsborough, N.C.
Selected Publications
The Delectable Mountains (1976)
Dingley Falls (1980)
Handling Sin (1983)
Time's Witness (1989)
Foolscap: Or, the Stages of Love (1991)
Uncivil Seasons (1993)
First Lady (2001)
Red Clay, Blue Cadillac: Stories of Twelve Southern Women (2002)
The Last Noel (2003)
The Killing Club (2005)
Collection Overview
Accession (2008-0186) (22,878 items; 30.5 lin. ft.; dated 1970s-2017) chiefly contains drafts and galleys of Malone's novels and other writings, personal and professional correspondence, and teaching materials. Also included are contracts and royalty statements, book tour materials and other promotional materials, videocassettes, audiocassettes, and digital files. The bulk of materials relate to Malone's career as a novelist and as a writer for the popular soap operas One Life to Live and Another World.
Accession (2009-0176) (750 items; 0.6 lin. ft.; dated 1980s) contains two binders of clippings, newspaper articles, reviews, and publicity for Malone's novels and plays from the 1980s. Also includes 1 videotape and 1 CD from One Life to Live.
Accession (2012-0052) (1875 items; 2.5 lin. ft.; dated 1980s-2011) contains incoming correspondence, clippings of reviews and profiles of Malone, and drafts of some of his works, including Four Corners of the Sky.
Acession (2017-0116) (3.5 lin. ft.; dated 1990s-2017) contains personal and professional correspondence; playscripts and screenplays of numerous works, including Handling Sin, Defender of the Faith, First Lady, White Trash Noir, and Washington Slept Here. Accession also contains financial information, public lectures and annotated readings, project proposals, sheet music, reviews, day planners and calendars, and personal photographs.
Conditions Governing Access
Some digital files and electronic records have been migrated to the library's server for preservation. Please contact Research Services to request access.
Videocassettes; Authors, American -- North Carolina; Audiocassettes; Television writers -- United States; Soap operas -- United States; Novelists -- North Carolina; Malone, Michael, 1942-
- Michael Malone Papers, 1970s-2000s, 437580; 51 boxes
  - Promotional material, 2000-2008, 437752 (Box 1)
  - Clippings, 437751 (Box 1)
  - Research notes, 437750 (Box 1)
  - Talks, 437749 (Box 1)
  - Book tour materials, 437748 (Box 1)
  - Scattered correspondence and fan mail, 437747 (Box 1)
  - Contracts and royalty statements (RESTRICTED), 1970s-2000s, 437746 (Box 2)
  - Hyperion Soap Book materials, 437745 (Box 3)
  - Selma Silverstein funeral service, 437744 (Box 3)
  - Carolina Anthology, 1994, 437743 (Box 3)
  - Promotional materials, 437742 (Box 3)
  - Writings, 437741 (Box 4)
  - The Way She Died, 437740 (Box 4)
  - Directories, 437739 (Box 4)
  - Personal and professional correspondence, 1990s-2000s, 437738 (Box 4)
  - Defender of the Faith, etc., 437737 (Box 4)
  - The Movie Making Marathon at Duke, 437736 (Box 5)
  - Personal correspondence, 1990s-2000, 437735 (Box 5)
  - North Carolina Writers' Network, 2006 Fall Conference, 437734 (Box 5)
  - Promotional materials and book jackets, 437733 (Box 5)
  - Red Clay and Blue Cadillac: Draft, 437732 (Box 6)
  - The Four Corners of the Sky: Draft, 437731 (Box 6)
  - The Four Corners of the Sky: Draft, 437730 (Box 7)
  - Red Clay and Blue Cadillac: Draft, 437729 (Box 7)
  - Other writings, 437728 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1989-1991, 437727 (Box 8)
  - Time's Witness: Partial draft, 437726 (Box 8)
  - The Art of Being Human: Draft, 1991, 437725 (Box 9)
  - Research materials and notes for Fiction's Map, 1981, 437724 (Box 9)
  - Animal Farm Revisited materials, 437723 (Box 9)
  - Junk: a Musical, 437722 (Box 9)
  - Talks, 437721 (Box 9)
  - Research materials for Fiction's Map, 1981, 437720 (Box 10)
  - Washington Slept Here: a screenplay, 437719 (Box 10)
  - Teaching materials, University of Pennsylvania, 437718 (Box 10)
  - Notes on Burnside in Hillsborough, N.C., 437717 (Box 10)
  - Ruin Creek by David Payne, 437716 (Box 11)
  - Notes and writings, 1980s-1990s, 437715 (Box 11)
  - Scattered correspondence, 1980s-1990s, 437714 (Box 11)
  - Correspondence, 1980s, 437713 (Box 12)
  - City of Angels: a musical, 437712 (Box 12)
  - Short stories and drafts, 437711 (Box 12)
  - Washington Slept Here: a screenplay, 437710 (Box 12)
  - Foolscap: Draft, 437709 (Box 13)
  - Unknown draft, 437708 (Box 13)
  - Playbills for musicals, 1980s-1990s, 437707 (Box 14)
  - Malone C.V., 437706 (Box 14)
  - The Scarlet Letter and Hearing the Call, 437705 (Box 14)
  - Scattered correspondence, 1990-1991, 437704 (Box 14)
  - Printed materials, 437703 (Box 14)
  - Writings, 437702 (Box 14)
  - Teaching materials, University of Pennsylvania, for courses on musicals and love and war, 1991, 437701 (Box 14)
  - One Life to Live: Notes and plot outlines, 437700 (Box 15)
  - Greeting cards, postcards, and personal correspondence, 437699 (Box 15)
  - Red Clay, 437698 (Box 15)
  - Haunts of Broadway, 1998, 437697 (Box 15)
  - The Killing Club: Draft, 437696 (Box 15)
  - The Last Noel: Draft, 437695 (Box 15)
  - Printed material, 437694 (Box 16)
  - Book tour materials, 437693 (Box 16)
  - The Last Noel: Draft, 437692 (Box 16)
  - Red Clay, Blue Cadillac: Draft, 437691 (Box 16)
  - Scattered correspondence, 2000s, 437690 (Box 16)
  - Painting the Roses Red: Draft, 1974, 437689 (Box 17)
  - Other drafts and notes, 437688 (Box 17)
  - Dingley on the Rampage: Draft, 437687 (Box 18)
  - Uncivil Seasons: Draft, 437686 (Box 18)
  - Other drafts and writings, 437685 (Box 18)
  - Correspondence, 1970s-1980s, 437684 (Box 19)
  - Notebook, 437683 (Box 19)
  - Scripts, drafts, and other writings, 437682 (Box 20)
  - Short stories, 1980s-1990s, 437681 (Box 20)
  - Defender of the Faith, etc.: Draft, 437680 (Box 21)
  - One Life to Live, 2002, 437679 (Box 21)
  - Correspondence, 1980s, 437678 (Box 21)
  - Other writings, 437677 (Box 21)
  - Correspondence, 1980s, 437676 (Box 22)
  - Writings, 1980s, 437675 (Box 22)
  - Dear Colleague: Draft, 437674 (Box 23)
  - Members Only: an Original Screenplay, 437673 (Box 23)
  - Annotated drafts, 437672 (Box 23)
  - Photograph contact sheets, 437671 (Box 23)
  - One Life to Live, 2002, 437670 (Box 23)
  - Defender of the Faith, etc., 1981, 437669 (Box 24)
  - Members Only, 437668 (Box 24)
  - Dingley Falls, 437667 (Box 24)
  - Dingley on the Rampage, 437666 (Box 25)
  - Photograph contact sheets, 1970s, 437665 (Box 25)
  - Other writings, 437664 (Box 25)
  - Thomas Berger materials, 437663 (Box 26)
  - Scattered correspondence, 1980s, 437662 (Box 26)
  - Clippings regarding Elvis' death, 1977, 437661 (Box 26)
  - Handling Sin: Draft, 437660 (Box 27)
  - Scattered correspondence, 1980s, 437659 (Box 27)
  - Negatives, 437658 (Box 28)
  - Dingley Falls: Draft, 437657 (Box 28)
  - City of Angels: Draft, 437656 (Box 28)
  - Clippings, 437655 (Box 28)
  - Time's Witness, 437654 (Box 29)
  - Junk: a musical, 437653 (Box 29)
  - Takeover, 437652 (Box 29)
  - Malone C.V., 437651 (Box 29)
  - Teaching Materials, Yale, 437650 (Box 29)
  - Washington Slept Here: notes, 437649 (Box 29)
  - City of Angels, 437648 (Box 29)
  - Scattered correspondence, 1970s-1980s, 437647 (Box 29)
  - The Widow's Mite, 437646 (Box 29)
  - Assorted writings, 437645 (Box 30)
  - Handling Sin, 437644 (Box 31)
  - Promotional materials, 437643 (Box 31)
  - Defender of the Faith, etc., 437642 (Box 31)
  - Publicity, 437641 (Box 31)
  - Correspondence, 1970s-1990s, 437640 (Box 32)
  - The Delectable Mountains, 437639 (Box 32)
  - Handling Sin, 437638 (Box 32)
  - Short stories, 437637 (Box 33)
  - Scattered correspondence, 1980s, 437636 (Box 33)
  - Book tours, 1990s, 437635 (Box 33)
  - Appearances, 1991-1992, 437634 (Box 34)
  - Correspondence, 1990s, 437633 (Box 34)
  - King of the Cats, 437632 (Box 34)
  - Defender of the Faith, etc., 437631 (Box 34)
  - Scattered correspondence, 1980s-1990s, 437630 (Box 35)
  - Dingley Falls, 437629 (Box 35)
  - Sea Moor Dunes: a play in 3 acts, 437628 (Box 35)
  - The Four Corners of the Sky, 437627 (Box 35)
  - Mrs. Wilder's Law, 437626 (Box 36)
  - Dingley Falls, 437625 (Box 36)
  - Pocket calendar, 1993-1994, 437624 (Box 36)
  - Defender of the Faith, etc., 437623 (Box 37)
  - Other writings, 437622 (Box 37)
  - Scattered correspondence, 437621 (Box 38)
  - The Delectable Mountains, 437620 (Box 38)
  - Other writings and short stories, 437619 (Box 38)
  - Defender of the Faith, etc., 437618 (Box 39)
  - Daytime Emmy Awards programs, 1991-1996, 437617 (Box 39)
  - Red Clay, Blue Cadillac, 437616 (Box 39)
  - Scattered correspondence, 437615 (Box 39)
  - Promotional materials, 437614 (Box 39)
  - Animal Farm Revisited, 437613 (Box 40)
  - Defender of the Faith, etc., 437612 (Box 40)
  - One Life to Live, 437611 (Box 40)
  - Handling Sin: Galley, 437610 (Box 40)
  - Other writings, 437609 (Box 40)
  - Notes, publicity, and promotional materials, 437608 (Box 40)
  - The Delectable Mountains: Galley, 437607 (Box 41)
  - Writings and notes, 437606 (Box 41)
  - Psychetypes: A New Way of Exploring Personality, 437605 (Box 42)
  - Animal Farm Revisited, 437604 (Box 42)
  - Other writings, 437603 (Box 42)
  - TV work (13 Bourbon Street), 437602 (Box 42)
  - Defender of the Faith, etc.: Draft, 437601 (Box 43)
  - 13 Bourbon Street: Scripts, 1996, 437600 (Box 43)
  - Time's Witness: notes, 437599 (Box 43)
  - Promotional materials, 437598 (Box 44)
  - Handling Sin, 437597 (Box 44)
  - 13 Bourbon Street: Scripts, 437596 (Box 44)
  - Animal Farm Revisited, 437595 (Box 44)
  - Scattered writings, 437594 (Box 45)
  - Foolscap: Proofs, 437593 (Box 46)
  - Foolscap: Proofs, 437592 (Box 47)
  - Defender of the Faith, etc.: Notes and drafts, 437591 (Box 47)
  - Newspaper clippings, 437590 (Box 47)
  - Playbills, 1970s-1990s, 437589 (Box 48)
  - One Life to Live and Another World, 437588; 12 VHS tapes (Box 49)
  - 13 Bourbon Street, Episode 1, 1997, 437587; Betacam SP (Box 49)
  - Author talks, 437586; 4 cassette tapes (Box 49)
  - Digital files, circa 1994-2006, 437585; about 150 floppy disks, 17 CDs, and 1 reel-to-reel audiotape (Box 50)
    Scope and Contents note
    Disks mostly include scripts and story outlines for One Life to Live, 13 Bourbon Street, and other Malone projects. Also included are novel drafts, some correspondence and memos, distribution lists, and other files.
    [NOTE: The content of all CDs and 50 selected floppy disks have been migrated to a library server. Consult a reference archivist for access to these electronic files.]
  - Handling Sin: Proof, 437584 (Box 51)
  - The Delectable Mountains: Proof, 437583 (Box 51)
  - Dingley Falls: Proof, 437582 (Box 51)
  - Clippings, 437581 (Box 51)
- Accession (2009-0176), 1980s, 437576; 1 box
  Accession (2009-0176) (750 items; 0.6 lin. ft.; dated 1980s) contains two binders of clippings, newspaper articles, reviews, and publicity for Malone's novels and plays from the 1980s. Also includes 1 videotape and 1 CD from One Life to Live.
  - Newspaper reviews, clippings, snippets, publicity materials, 1980s, 437579 (Box 52)
  - One Life to Live Christmas Reel, 2003 (videotape), 437578 (Box 52)
  - 13 Bourbon Street Ep. 001, 1997 (CD), 437577 (Box 52)
- Accession (2012-0052), 437538; 3 boxes
  Accession (2012-0052) (1875 items; 2.5 lin. ft.; dated 1980s-2011) contains incoming correspondence, clippings of reviews and profiles of Malone, and drafts of some of his works, including Four Corners of the Sky.
  - Correspondence, unsorted, 1985-1990, 437575; 6 folders (Box 53)
  - Correspondence, 2008, 437574 (Box 53)
  - Correspondence, 2009, 437573 (Box 53)
  - Correspondence, 2010, 437572 (Box 53)
  - Correspondence, 2011-2012, 437571 (Box 53)
  - Malone's appearances/programs, 437570 (Box 53)
  - Publicity for Malone's programs, 437569 (Box 53)
  - Clippings with Malone's press coverage and profiles, 437568 (Box 53)
  - Programs and flyers for events Malone attended, 437567 (Box 53)
  - Edgars mystery awards programs, 437566 (Box 53)
  - FK Parters reports, 2009, 437565 (Box 53)
  - Publisher invoices, 437564 (Box 53)
  - Washington Slept Here drafts and notes, 437563; 3 folders (Box 53)
  - City of the Angels drafts and notes, 437562; 2 folders (Box 53)
  - Draft of unknown title, 437561 (Box 53)
  - Time's Witness draft, 437560 (Box 53)
  - Essays and short stories, 437559 (Box 53)
  - Scripts and proposals for musicals, 437558 (Box 53)
  - The Four Corners of the Sky drafts, unsorted, 437557; 5 folders (Box 54)
  - Dear Colleague background research, 437556 (Box 54)
  - Reviews of other works, by Malone, 437555; 2 folders (Box 54)
  - First Lady reviews, 2001, 437554 (Box 55)
  - Handling Sin publicity and advertisements, 437553 (Box 55)
  - Handling Sin fan mail, 1986-1987, 437552 (Box 55)
  - Handling Sin reviews, 1986, 437551 (Box 55)
  - House of Blue Leaves galleys, 437550 (Box 55)
  - Uncivil Season reviews, 2011 and undated, 437549 (Box 55)
  - Dingley Falls galleys, 437548 (Box 55)
  - Time's Witness reviews, 1989, 437547 (Box 55)
  - The Four Corners of the Sky publicity, 437546 (Box 55)
  - The Four Corners of the Sky reviews, 2009, 437545 (Box 55)
  - Clearing Waters, by M. Burakow and N. Hawthorne, 437544 (Box 55)
  - The Night Santa Claus Fell from the Sky, 437543 (Box 55)
  - Notes, drafts, and fragments, 437542 (Box 55)
  - Revelers Club, 2011, 437541 (Box 55)
  - Miscellaneous ephemera, 437540 (Box 55)
  - DVDs of Malone's appearances, 437539 (Box 55)
    Conditions Governing Access note
    [Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Use of these materials may require production of listening or viewing copies. Please contact Research Services before coming to use this collection.]
- Accession (2017-0116), 1980s-2015 and undated; 1; 3 boxes
  Scope and Contents
  Acession (2017-0116) (3.5 lin. ft.; dated 1990s-2017) contains personal and professional correspondence; playscripts and screenplays of numerous works, including Handling Sin, Defender of the Faith, First Lady, White Trash Noir, and Washington Slept Here. Accession also contains financial information, public lectures and annotated readings, project proposals, sheet music, reviews, day planners and calendars, and personal photographs.
  - An American in Paris treatment, Undated (Box 56)
  - Animal Farm Revisited script, synopsis, and correspondence, 1988; 2 folders (Box 56)
    Script, synopsis, and correspondence related to London production
  - Charles Dickens: A Christmas Carol scripts, revisions and final, 2011; 3 folders (Box 56)
    Four scripts
  - City of the Angels script, Undated (Box 56)
    "Seeing With the Eye": Job in the Modern Novel
  - First Lady promotional packet, 2001 (Box 56)
    Includes pamphlets and press material
  - Defender of the Faith screenplay, 1983; 3 folders (Box 56)
    Two screenplays
  - Guys and Dolls sheet music and script, Undated (Box 56)
  - Handling Sin screenplays, 1987; 9 folders (Box 56)
    Two screenplays, full typescript, front matter, and promotional materials
  - Hate Mail proposal, 2006 (Box 56)
    Includes notes and synopsis
  - Huckleberry Finn play script, Undated (Box 56)
  - Finances, 2008--2009 (Box 56)
    Earnings and royalty statements from investments
  - Killing Club, 2004 (Box 56)
    Contract Correspondence
  - Duke in New York, 2010 (Box 56)
    Lectures, correspondence, and travel plans
  - Carousel script, 2012 (Box 56)
    Includes program, cast notes, and sheet music
  - Intellectual Statement, Undated (Box 56)
  - Curriculum Vitae, ca. 2000 (Box 56)
  - Doe Branch Writing Retreat, 2011 (Box 56)
  - Christmas at Mysterious Bookshop, 2011 (Box 56)
  - Cinderella production, 2012-2014 (Box 56)
    Material related to Broadway production of Rodgers and Hamemrstein's "Cindrella"
  - One Life to Live material, 2004 (Box 56)
    Contact list, shooting schedule, ID card
  - Political Contributions, 2016 (Box 56)
    Response letters from campaigns of Josh Stein and Roy Cooper
  - Washington Slept Here screenplays, 1985; 2 folders (Box 57)
  - Guys and Dolls sheet music, Undated (Box 57)
  - Event programs and playbills, 2009-2017; 3 folders (Box 57)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1991-2016; 4 folders (Box 57)
    Letters, notes, holiday cards, birthday greetings
  - Novel Covers, ca. 1987 (Box 57)
    Hardback and paperback covers for "Handling Sin" and handmade promo
  - Festival of Faith and Writing, 2004 (Box 57)
    Conference material
  - Periodicals, 2005-2015 (Box 57)
  - Bali Hai sheet music and lyrics, Undated (Box 57)
  - Writers Guild of America, 2007 (Box 57)
    Includes materials related to pension plan
  - The Century Association, 2005 (Box 57)
    Membership packet for private dining club
  - Public readings and lectures, Undated; 11 folders (Box 57)
    Includes photocopies of pages from Michael Malone novels and short stories for public readings with annotations, selections include pages from "Chairman", "Handling Sin", "First Lady", "Four Corners of the Sky", "Red Clay," "Foolscap," Crystal Coast, "Nicholas Nickleby," F. Scott Fitzgerald, 5 Ps, Home for the Holidays, Raleigh Fine Arts Talk, South Talk, Literary Talk, "Mad Dog Malone", "Our Mothers...", Elizabeth Spencer, Duke Reads "The Maltese Falcon", and "Philadelphia--City of Big Beginnings"
  - Poetry, Undated (Box 57)
    No author attribution, poems include "Like a Rose to the Sun", "Vienna", "Darkwood", "Same River Twice",
  - The Maltese Falcon musical proposal, 2009 (Box 57)
    Proposal for a musical adaptation of "The Maltese Falcon" including handwritten notes
  - What's Wrong with Happiness? sheet music with lyrics, Undated (Box 57)
  - The Music Man script, 2011 (Box 58)
    Multiple annotated printouts of Act 1
  - The Retreat at Key Points play script, Undated; 2 folders (Box 58)
    Two drafts
  - Waiting for Godot script, Undated (Box 58)
    Two scripts
  - Trinity Playhouse proposal, Undated (Box 58)
  - White Trash Noir play script, Undated; 4 folders (Box 58)
    Three scripts
  - The Way She Died play script, Undated (Box 58)
    Includes annotations and production notes
  - Fiona Delancy The Way She Died play script, Undated (Box 58)
    Printed play script pasted into small notebook
  - red clay, blue cadillac, 2002 (Box 58)
    Published collection of short stories
  - BOOKMARKS festival packet, 2012 (Box 58)
    Includes correspondence and notes
  - Murphy Radio Show script, Undated (Box 58)
  - Calendars and day planners, 1989-2003 (Box 58)
    Calendar from 1989; day planners from 1992 and 2003
  - Calendar, 1993 (Oversize-folder 1)
    Large calendar from 1993
  - Reviews and Correspondence, 1991-2005 (Box 58)
    Book reviews, drafts, and photocopies of newspaper reviews, includes correspondence with reviewers and agents
  - James M. Cain talk, Undated (Box 58)
    Notes and slides from author talk at Regulator Bookshop
  - Miscellaneous, 2000 (Box 58)
    Cards, nametags, and professional membership cards
  - I Can't Give You Anything But Love sheet music, Undated (Box 58)
    Two copies
  - First Lady typescript, Undated; 4 folders (Box 58)
    Annotated, incomplete, pages 52-536
  - Personal Photographs, 1998-2015 (Box 58)